Hello and welcome to another walk through of
computer architecture for everybody. This is
a walk through of our VLSI design layout tool very
large scale integration. The tool where we sort of
build circuits by painting layers that turn into
photo-liththography. Although it's probably these
days laser lithography, but you get the idea.
So the the basic idea is you can draw these pure
areas that are going to have metal placed on them.
You can also erase them. And it doesn't really
matter how you place them. As long as you erase
them and put them together, you can end up with
quite weird shapes. I'll put some positive voltage
in one area. And you see the positive voltage goes
wherever the metal is. Even though the way I drew
it was I drew a piece, then I chopped a piece out
of it, etc., etc. So, let me clear this all out
and let me work on a not gate because a no tgate
is is a pretty good and simple way to understand
how this things works. So you could take a look at
the the image from the lecture and paint exactly
the thing it does and that's a good good thing to
do. But I'm going to do it a little differently.
I'm going to start from the transistors outward.
And so I'm going to start with the PPOS transistor
at the top. So I'm going to have a vertical bit
of P-doped silicon. And then I'm going to
make a vertical piece of Nope silicon. And
then I'm going to take some polysilicon and run
across because where the intersection happens
with between a polysilicon and an ndoped and a
polysilicon and a p-doped that's where transistors
happen. So at these two intersections there are
transistors. Okay. And so if we take a look at the
layers we can see because there's always
this layer viewer. This layer viewer says,
"Oh, there's some P diffusion." And now we've got
some P diffusion touching polysilicon which makes
a PMOS transistor. Then we have N-doped diffusion.
We have some polysilicon and then when they touch
when they cover each other up then there is an
NMOS transistor that is created. So we now have
Oh, I got to erase that. You can just erase stuff
if you mess it up. So now what we got to do is we
got to get some electricity to these. So we got to
draw the rest of the circuit. Okay. So, the first
thing I'm going to do is I'm going to draw the
output and that's going to be a bit of metal. So,
I overlap the metal with the P diffusion and the
N diffusion. Now, if I take a look at the layers,
you see that where I overlap the metal and the P
diffusion, there's still a gap. And where I metal
met the N diffusion and the metal, there's still a
gap. If I want to actually connect them together,
I have to explicitly connect them together. So I
am going to do that by punching a VIA. It's like
drilling a little hole and then pouring I don't
know metal into it. But so now what we have is we
have the P diffusion overlapping the metal and
the N diffusion overlapping the metal. But now
there's a little connector that goes down through
the center. So we are working in three dimensions
here. They're all kind of layered on top of
one another. But then we want to connect the
layers. Away we go. Okay. So now I want to
actually make some input. So I'm going to take the
input these two polysilicons and then I'll just
drop a little input out here a little bit. And so
the polysilicon and the metal do not touch until
I punch a VIA there. So I punch a little hole,
punch a little hole, and away we go. And then the
next thing I want to do is I want to have a place
to get the output. So, I'll pull a little bit of
metal out here. Um, metal touching metal doesn't
need a via. So, we're pretty much almost done
at this point. If we put some voltage up here
in the orange in the P-Doped silicon and we put
some ground at the bottom in the N-doped silicon,
what you see is the the voltage is flowing, but
because there's no voltage on the transistor,
the transistor ends up being a block to the whole
thing. Okay? So if you recall the the PMOS is open
on ground and closed on positive and the NMOS is
the opposite where it is open on positive and I
mean closed on positive uh closed on ground
and opened on positive. I messed myself up.
So let's just go ahead and put some voltage in. I
probably should have done that. So now you see the
transistor in operation. So I've got voltage on
the input and that is causing the upper transistor
to block voltage from flowing. So voltage would
come into the PMOS transistor but not leave the
transistor. If we then look at the NMOS transistor
in the bottom you see the ground is flowing up
but in this case it's flowing through the NMOS
transistor to the output and so the output is is
negative. Now, if we switch and put ground as the
input, which we do like that, then you see that
the PMOS at the top is conducting and the plus
is going all the way out to the output. Um, oops,
I just put a ground there. That messes that thing
up. And but I can fix that. Watch. I can just say
erase. Come back. Come back. I just hovered and
hit it. So, I erased that guy. So, now it's back
to being a happy little not gate. Okay. So, that's
a happy little not gate. Um, let's go ahead and
turn this in for our assignment. It tells you
to place a probe with a label A on the input
to your not gate. So, there's a thing called a
probe and we're going to replace this ground with
input A and it says place a probe with a label
Q on the output. So, we got A and Q. So, now I
think we're in good shape. We already built the we
already built the not gate and we tested it. So,
let's just go ahead and start the grading. So, it
checks to see if there's an A and a Q probe. And
we named them correctly. Doesn't know we may
have them have them in the wrong place. We're
we're set A to ground and it check to see if the
output is VCC, which is right. That's the first
half of the Not. Now, it checks sets A to VCC
and then set checks to see if the Q is ground.
And that's correct. And so, we are done and we
have earned our grade. So before I stop here,
a couple other things to show you. There is this
really cool feature called Read Circuit. And I'm
going to press it and then just stay quiet.
Draw VCC at (8, 1). Draw probe A at (4, 6)
with voltage VCC. Draw P plus diffusion from (8,
1) to (8, 5). Draw polyilicon from (6, 3) to (10,
3). Draw polyilicon from (6, 9) to (10, 9). Draw
metal from (6, 3) to (6, 9). Draw metal from (8,
5) to (8, 7). Draw metal from (4, 6) to (6,6).
Draw metal from (8, 6) to (11, 6) draw VIA (6,
3) draw via (8, 5) draw VIA (8, 7) draw via (6, 9)
draw probe A (4, 6) with voltage VCC draw probe Q
at (11, 6) with voltage zero Draw N plus diffusion
from (8, 7) to (8, 12). Draw GND at (11, 1).
So that's pretty cool. There's also a way for
you to load and save. This is going to use
um space on your um on your browser. This is using
what's called browser local storage.
So I'll just call this one not two.
And so if you look and do load, you could reload
to not two. So I'll just leave that for a bit.
So then the one last thing I will show you uh is
there is this command line. And so you can type um
you can type commands here. I'm going to say draw
metal from (2, 2) to (10, 10). This is going to
ruin my circuit, but you'll get the idea. So that
just drew the metal and so I messed up my whole
circuit. Um, but you can see that you could place
these things. So if I started over from scratch,
I could type draw draw poly silicon from (3, 6) to
(10, 6). See? So you could draw all those things
and um that's actually what the uh the save and
the restore actually return knows all of those
uh items. So there's some help for this that you
might find uh useful. Talks a lot about how to do
stuff. It gives you hints as to how to complete
your homework etc. So um I hope you found this
interesting this walk through on the VLSI design
system for uh computer architecture for everybody.